<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>PhDJournal | Tanya Does Science</title>
    <link>/tag/phdjournal/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/phdjournal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>PhDJournal</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon.png</url>
      <title>PhDJournal</title>
      <link>/tag/phdjournal/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fast-tracking the PhD Experience</title>
      <link>/post/fast-tracking-the-phd-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/fast-tracking-the-phd-experience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Can I just humorously preface this by saying that the email from the journal saying that they had received the manuscript addressed me as Dr Strydom and can&amp;rsquo;t say that I hate it - although maybe a &lt;em&gt;bit&lt;/em&gt; premature 😉 Oh and maybe as another add on - working in different timezones may be annoying in terms of scheduling meetings but it is pretty great when you wake up in the mornings to &amp;lsquo;good job&amp;rsquo; messages from your supervisor ☺️&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not going to talk about the actual theory/content of the manuscript (because that I&amp;rsquo;m saving for the actual project page) but rather just talk about how being thrown into the deep end by your supervisor (but having him also throw you a very effective form of floatation device) results in quickly learning things in a driven manner, especially some handy collaborative workflow things that are also very Open Science and FAIR aligned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;publishing-so-soon&#34;&gt;Publishing so soon?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look I&amp;rsquo;m not saying that all graduate students &lt;strong&gt;need&lt;/strong&gt; to publish something right of the bat - and its a case of student readiness and opportunity that needs to be taken into consideration. However, that being said it makes for a fun way to help and encourage the student to get up to speed with literature and have it be in a rewarding manner (in a sense) as the student has a short-term goal to achieve. I also felt like it took away some of the daunting feeling of &amp;lsquo;where do we even start?&amp;rsquo; after starting. It&amp;rsquo;s also a really great confidence boost and makes you feel like a &amp;lsquo;scientist&amp;rsquo;. Ultimately it also means that I have something &amp;lsquo;to show&amp;rsquo; when I take my candidacy exam in a few months time - hopefully impressing the advisory board 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;new-coding-language---sure-why-not&#34;&gt;New coding language - sure why not?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I knew going into this that learning how to work in &lt;code&gt;Julia&lt;/code&gt; was going to be inevitable - &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;it&amp;rsquo;s the way&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;/author/poisot-lab/&#34;&gt;Poisot Lab&lt;/a&gt; after all. However, that being said learning, and &lt;del&gt;struggling&lt;/del&gt; pottering along with a new coding language when the submission deadline is seemingly in the distance is all fun and games, when its two days before d-day - not so fun. But overall its nice to work on a small, manageable chunk of the Julia-verse and a lot of the functions I was writing were simple arithmetic so it was a nice to work in a &amp;lsquo;low stakes&amp;rsquo; situation with regards to getting to grips with how to write function and the &amp;lsquo;types&amp;rsquo; that you can specify in &lt;code&gt;Julia&lt;/code&gt;. It also helps that after my toddler like attempt at writing a function  my supervisor steps in and directs/shows me where I erred or what is a more &amp;lsquo;grammatically correct&amp;rsquo; way of approaching the problem. Essentially I had a small and &amp;lsquo;contained&amp;rsquo; crash course in a new programming language that will hopefully set me up for success further down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;are-you-not-entertained&#34;&gt;Are you not entertained?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know what&amp;rsquo;s the best part of my fast-tracked experience? It&amp;rsquo;s really helped build back some of the excitement and enjoyment for research and science-ing that I felt my masters had &amp;lsquo;taken&amp;rsquo; from me. It also helps that my supervisor is very excited about everything we&amp;rsquo;ve done and I can&amp;rsquo;t help but feed off of that! It&amp;rsquo;s also very entertaining collaborating over GitHub with someone for both coding and writing and let me tell you its getting even more exciting regarding GitHub collaborating for our next project (The predicting ecological networks one if you&amp;rsquo;re wondering). I think (hopefully one day) I&amp;rsquo;ll write up a quick primer on collaborative writing over GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tanya 🐾&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>And we&#39;re off! 🐎</title>
      <link>/post/and-were-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/and-were-off/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I now have an institution email address (and for the first time it&amp;rsquo;s my full name and not just a series of numbers!) and a student number so arguably it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;real real&amp;rsquo; and I&amp;rsquo;m now &lt;em&gt;officially&lt;/em&gt; a PhD student. Although I haven&amp;rsquo;t joined the lab yet in the physical sense I&amp;rsquo;m definitely part of the online office space and have successfully navigated a few meetings. The most recent being one with my supervisor where he suggested that we get started with a &amp;lsquo;short but cool project&amp;rsquo; that would help me get familiar with ecological networks, some linear algebra, working in Julia and of course making what would be considered a valuable and interesting contribution to science (Just to add to that we as a lab have a workshop scheduled in October with two other labs looking at making predictions in ecological networks - so a lot lined up for the rest of the year).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s cool though - instead of bombarding me with a stack of literature and no real &amp;lsquo;idea&amp;rsquo; as to where we are going with my PhD project I have the chance to passively do my required literature reading along with some other skills development in a fun, directed and rewarding (&lt;del&gt;should&lt;/del&gt; when we publish) manner. This also feels more meaningful somehow? The bigger goal of course is so that I can walk into the meeting with my advisory committee later in the winter term with a more concrete product to show them as opposed to (well maybe more in addition to) showcasing what I have read or thought about regarding my PhD project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to this (and as I alluded to earlier) the lab also has a workshop planned for October that is also slated as a way for me to get more familiar with the current state of networks in ecology and the associated prediction methods. This also gives me the opportunity to work with some of the Poisot lab members (which I think given the current situation will be beneficial for me to get to know everyone better and feel like part of the team) as well as meeting students and researchers from the other two labs. Currently the idea is that we produce a paper at the end of this workshop - which will be lead by the students/early career researchers of the different labs. Again an awesome opportunity to feel like I&amp;rsquo;m doing meaningful work while still doing the traditionally &amp;lsquo;required reading&amp;rsquo; as an early PhD student.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So all in all I&amp;rsquo;ve started the &amp;lsquo;marathon&amp;rsquo; that is my PhD journey and at this point there are a lot of interesting things front and centre and I&amp;rsquo;m chomping at the bit to get going!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;#WatchThisSpace&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tanya 🐾&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
