<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tanya Strydom | Tanya Does Science</title>
    <link>/author/tanya-strydom/</link>
      <atom:link href="/author/tanya-strydom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Tanya Strydom</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 09:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon.png</url>
      <title>Tanya Strydom</title>
      <link>/author/tanya-strydom/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking FAIR and open science to the field - The evolution of the PFTC field course</title>
      <link>/talk/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2020 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/example/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making better predictions of ecological networks through machine learning (done right)</title>
      <link>/project/networkpredictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/networkpredictions/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Generalities between ecological networks and complexity</title>
      <link>/project/svdnetworks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/svdnetworks/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data are the sheet music and data visualisation is the symphony</title>
      <link>/post/data-are-the-sheet-music-and-data-visualisation-is-the-symphony/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/data-are-the-sheet-music-and-data-visualisation-is-the-symphony/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m definitely not the first (nor will I be the last) person to try and draw links between science and music but a recent(ish) tweet by Richard McElreath got me thinking on the idea a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;
&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
Many performers of music cannot read it. Okay. There are other, often more intuitive, ways to learn music.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Scientists perform stat models. Most scientists cannot read them. This is less OK, but there are other ways to learn models.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Short thread in which I strain this comparison &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/WP8m6554PQ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/WP8m6554PQ&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
— Richard McElreath 🦔 (&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@rlmcelreath&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rlmcelreath/status/1284426933749653504?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 18, 2020&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this thread McElreath discusses the similarities between reading sheet music and mathematical notations - if you don’t know where to start it can all be pretty daunting and even if you do know where to start you don’t necessarily read it ‘word-for-word’. Now, as someone who dabbles in both sides of this argument I couldn’t agree more. Mathematical notation can be pretty scary, but if you look for patterns/elements that you recognise you can work out what the model is telling you and the same can be said when I’m looking at sheet music. The same goes with regards to the ‘degrees of separation’ and sheet music/models that are closer to my area of study/instrument of choice require less work to ‘decode’ than those that may be drastically different. McElreath goes on to discuss ‘maths anxiety’ and how that may be off-putting (or even scary for some) and actually decreases the liklihood of someone reading an article (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pnas.org/content/109/29/11735&#34;&gt;Fawcett and Higginson, 2012&lt;/a&gt;). He also mentions maybe making mathematical notation more palatable - and here is where he caught my attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hans Rosling has also made links to science and music:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Most of us need to listen to the music to understand how beautiful it is. But often that’s how we present statistics: we just show the notes, we don’t play the music.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and his argument is perhaps a bit more elegantly phrased and absolutely nails it if you ask me. If statistics (or equations and models) is the sheet music then we as the scientists or researchers are the conductors. It is the responsibility (and vision) of the conductor to translate what he sees on paper and make it art as well as something the general public can perceive and enjoy. The conductor does this by directing and ‘using’ the musicians to create the final product. The reason I use an orchestra here as opposed to a single musician here in my analogy is that I feel there are many ‘tools’ we can use to communicate the ‘scary maths’ and what we can learn from it, and much like how some scores play to the strengths of certain instruments so do some of the communication tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having just said that I’m going to focus in on my all time favourite way of communicating science - visually! Hans Rosling is well known for his excellent visualisations - and data visualisation as a whole is on the rise (I regularly end up just oogling some of the beautiful infographics to be found on the web). A quick google search will yield multiple hits of different websites listing their top DataViz books - mostly focused on showcasing business data. Yet why have the sciences seemingly lagged behind - at least when it comes to journal articles? There are many beautiful examples of infographics that communicate results for popular science articles but journal articles tend to keep things very ‘vanilla’. With most (if not all) people accessing articles or resources online we are no longer restricted by printing or fitting figures and tables onto pages. We could potentially even embed links that lead to interactive dashboard-type applications (allowing people to play with a model y changing inputs/variables and see what it does and how various parameters are related) or even use animations. There are naturally some other concerns that need to be taken into account, such as accessibility and limited connectivity but as it stands there is no reason we cannot at least attempt to add richer visuals elements to our work. I think visual abstracts are a step in the right direction but what is to say we cannot extend this same ‘light hearted’ approach to the manuscript itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve always joked that one day I will write a totally visual manuscript (Intro = digram/flowchart, Methods = schematic diagram, Results = plots and tables, and Discussion = diagram/flowchart) The thinking behind this is that I find it easier to articulate myself in a visual manner and almost all of my writing starts with me drawing a picture of what I plan on saying. This of course also means that I find it easier to visualise/draw what I am learning or reading as well - so it only stands to reason that the more visual elements a manuscript has the easier it is for me (and likely others) to get the bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I guess what this boils down to is me challenging us to think about how we can make beautiful music that can be appreciated by a broader audience and ask if we are getting the best out of our orchestra. Having a visual aid that is well designed can break down at least some of the language barriers and make out work easier to understand for a non-native speaker, we are ‘forced’ to cut out a lot of jargon which makes our work more interpretable across disciplines - or even less experienced individuals (I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don’t want to say non-scientists) or students and in a way we have to think harder about what our data are telling us, because if we don’t understand what is going it makes it very hard to translate that into a picture. Finally, to bring it back to the music analogy - much like how I would annotate my sheet music to make it easier to interpret we can also add other aids (annotations) along with our visualisations to help make the interpretation process easier - much like many infographics do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is me challenging us to play with our data a bit more and see what it wants to show us - and it doesn’t have to be fancy it can start with playing with colours and then the more comfortable you get the more you can stretch you boundaries. This is where projects like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tidytuesday.com&#34;&gt;#TidyTuesday&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.makeovermonday.co.uk&#34;&gt;#MakeoverMonday&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.storytellingwithdata.com/swdchallenge&#34;&gt;Story Telling with Data challenge&lt;/a&gt; are really fun - you can play with data in a ‘low pressure’ environment and get inspiration from others as to how they approached the same challenge and help you familiarize yourself with different plot types along with what works and what doesn’t. This helps you develop a library of sorts along with a bit of a personal style - much like how a conductor adds his own flair to sonata/concerto you can make your data visualisation your own! The next step of course (and this is me calling myself out) is taking the same playful approach when writing manuscripts for publication and instead of ‘throwing in’ a boxplot or two thinking of a better way that I can use that space (and time) to visually tell my story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have fun creating and pushing the envelope for data visualisation in science!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🐾
Tanya&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TidyTuesday</title>
      <link>/project/tidytuesday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/tidytuesday/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How COVID-19 possibly enhanced my educational experience: the post-course musings of a COVID-19 refugee</title>
      <link>/post/how-covid-19-possibly-enhanced-my-educational-experience-the-post-course-musings-of-a-covid-19-refugee/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/how-covid-19-possibly-enhanced-my-educational-experience-the-post-course-musings-of-a-covid-19-refugee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of this course the thought of me sharing my experiences and being a (somewhat) active member of the science community on ‘The Twitter’ never crossed my mind. Yet, after my (unexpectedly) extended stay in Peru for the PFTC 5 course I think I’m getting the hang of this tweeting thing and it might be here to stay…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it’s fair to say that a reoccurring theme with this course was the unexpected and far reaching consequences of the COVID-19 pandemic. Not only did we have some direct changes to our actual trip and travel itinerary (with some of us leaving early and others having an extended stay), COVID-19 also changed my view of science and showed me the importance of the connections and networks of the scientific community. Essentially (at least to me now) science is more than just doing cool research and getting published, it’s about sharing your data and findings and working in a collaborative environment. I’ve never had to share my code with anyone (and my coding etiquette reflects that) and now I just want to or need to share everything (after extensive revisions of course). In addition, although I’m no longer having my three-hour breakfasts, I do still make an effort to check what is happening on #ScienceTwitter during this time and who knows maybe one day I’ll start tweeting about my own research and not just #Quarantrait or #COVID19refugee life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess what I’m getting at is that although my main goals for this course were ‘science’ related – and don’t get me wrong I did learn a lot about the science side of things – I think I stepped away from this course with a much better understanding of both the ‘real’ science behind functional traits along with a better understanding of what it is like doing science in a collaborative world. So as much as the COVID-19 pandemic got in the way of us doing the science we had originally set out to do (but we did make the best of a less than ideal situation) I would dare to say that we (or at least I) still stepped away from this course with an unexpected but comprehensive learning experience. I would even go so far as to speculate that the networks we established during this course may be stronger than those of previous courses given our shared experiences through this pandemic – be it virtual or together in the courtyard of the Royal Inka I. Let’s just say I am very keen to see how far these relationships and collaborative efforts will go!&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-although-our-time-in-the-field-was-cut-short-we-did-manage-to-get-all-of-the-important-things-done-namely-gush-over-adorable-plants-play-in-the-mountains-ogle-microlandscapes-and-some-actual-science-of-course&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/Picture1.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Although our time in the field was cut short, we did manage to get all of the important things done namely: gush over adorable plants, play in the mountains, ogle microlandscapes and some actual science of course!&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/Picture1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Although our time in the field was cut short, we did manage to get all of the important things done namely: gush over adorable plants, play in the mountains, ogle microlandscapes and some actual science of course!
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before starting this course, we were asked to set some personal goals, so I guess it’s only fair to take a moment to reflect on them – funnily enough these were very much focused on the ‘real’ science side of things! I had previously told myself that I would consider this course a success if I walked away from this course being more confident in linking functional traits to broader ecosystem processes (and would be confident in applying the knowledge to my own research) and also having applied myself (read: being slightly less disorganised) by assisting in the administrative side of things such as the writing of data documentation and being part of the data curation process. I think given the circumstances we did a pretty good job of helping me realise my goals – especially on the data curation side of things. Also, I did mention that I was looking forward to making a new host of international friends and that can definitely be ticked off!&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-some-typical-scenes-from-the-quarantrait-life-including-zoom-meetingslectures-keeping-the-trait-wheel-turning-chatting-up-a-storm-with-the-breakfast-club-and-carrying-on-with-real-world-work&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/Picture2.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;Some typical scenes from the #Quarantrait life including Zoom meetings/lectures, keeping the trait wheel turning, chatting up a storm with the breakfast club and carrying on with ‘real world’ work&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/Picture2.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Some typical scenes from the #Quarantrait life including Zoom meetings/lectures, keeping the trait wheel turning, chatting up a storm with the breakfast club and carrying on with ‘real world’ work
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guess it only fair to finish this post up with a bit of personal reflection upon having society and the world you know being flipped upside down by a pandemic. Spending 17 days in a government enforced lockdown means there is a lot of time for self-reflection and maybe just a hint of soul searching. Personally, I don’t think I was that perturbed by my new (and restricted) living conditions although a think that might be my ‘distance from the equator’ theory at play there (which might need to get its own blog post at some point…). Well that or I am really good at compartmentalising problems and keeping myself oblivious to things… I find that I managed to keep going on with ‘business as usual’ and think I may have actually been more productive!  Especially now in the second phase of my global pandemic journey where I’ve taken on refugee-like status with family friends in the UK countryside. Also, funnily enough, as disorganised and scatter-brained as I might be at times, I did find that I do need to have some structure and control in my life – in this case taking control of our morning Zoom meetings!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I think as much of a disturbance (annoyance) the COVID-19 pandemic has been both with regards to disrupting the original course plan and keeping me from getting home I think there are many positives that come from this as well. We still managed to get the teaching done and I’ve gained new insights to the (important) social side of science all while making some (hopefully) long-lasting connections. And lastly - as well as the most important I am going to be able to put proficient in Zoom on my CV. Who knows in the new post COVID-19 world it might be a highly sought-after skill!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you guys on ‘The Twitter’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🐾
Tanya&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goodbye icky Swedish winter and hello to mountains and continued learning</title>
      <link>/post/goodbye-icky-swedish-winter-and-hello-to-mountains-and-continued-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/goodbye-icky-swedish-winter-and-hello-to-mountains-and-continued-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s &lt;em&gt;‘sportlov’&lt;/em&gt; week in Stockholm, which is essentially winter break for the school kids and is traditionally the sports holidays and most families go on their annual ski trip. Although the Masters students don’t officially have a winter holiday to look forward to, I can’t help but share in the excitement of the kids as I to prepare for my own winter holiday of sorts. In less than a week I will be trading in the homogenous urban landscape of Stockholm for the mountainous Puna grasslands of Peru. Here I will be ‘going back to school’ for a bit as I take a break from thesis writing and get my hands dirty as we go out into the field to collect data and conduct mini research projects with the &lt;a href=&#34;/author/pftcourses/&#34;&gt;PFTCourses&lt;/a&gt; team for their fifth Plant Functional traits course. Aside from getting to play in the mountains (all in the name of science) I’m also excited to meet the students and instructors from different countries and scientific backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;





  
  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-some-mountains-from-back-home-in-south-africa-where-i-did-my-undergraduate-research-fun-fact-for-those-that-are-familiar-with-the-marvel-cinematic-universe-this-area-is-canonically-the-foot-slopes-of-wakanda-yes-my-study-area-is-world-famous-how-about-yours-&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/post/goodbye-icky-swedish-winter-and-hello-to-mountains-and-continued-learning/featured_hufeddb77f1eb00da1dd346c1f3e0fb87b_10173630_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpeg&#34; data-caption=&#34;Some mountains from back home in South Africa where I did my undergraduate research. Fun fact for those that are familiar with the Marvel cinematic universe this area is canonically the foot slopes of Wakanda. Yes, my study area is world famous how about yours? 😉&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img data-src=&#34;/post/goodbye-icky-swedish-winter-and-hello-to-mountains-and-continued-learning/featured_hufeddb77f1eb00da1dd346c1f3e0fb87b_10173630_2000x2000_fit_q90_lanczos.jpeg&#34; class=&#34;lazyload&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; width=&#34;5220&#34; height=&#34;2936&#34;&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Some mountains from back home in South Africa where I did my undergraduate research. Fun fact for those that are familiar with the Marvel cinematic universe this area is canonically the foot slopes of Wakanda. Yes, my study area is world famous how about yours? 😉
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am an ecologist by training and love seeing how everything fits together – the thing that gets me most excited though? How the microclimate affects the performance of plants and, if you really want to get me excited throw some biotic interactions into the mix. Both elements that have followed me throughout my Honours project in South Africa, a stint in the Sub-Antarctic and now for my Masters thesis in Sweden. Although this course isn’t specifically dealing with microclimates and biotic interactions it is dealing with the plant performance side of things. Specifically, using functional traits to aid in quantifying ‘performance’. Along with learning how to go out and record these functional traits (some of which I have never worked before) we will also be working on data management (something my scatter-brained self does not do well) and obviously writing up a small research project. I will count this trip as a ‘success’ if I can confidently measure traits other than SLA and LDMC and link them to bigger ecosystem processes (this means I would be confident in using them in my own research) and publishing a data paper will at least allow me to feel as if I’ve done some part in managing data so that it is in a publishable format.&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-one-of-the-best-parts-about-working-with-microclimates-all-of-the-awesome-microlandscapes-you-get-acquainted-with-working-at-such-small-scales-means-you-often-get-to-appreciate-the-little-things-in-life-as-you-sometimes-spend-half-an-hour-without-moving-more-than-a-meter&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/Collage1.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;One of the best parts about working with microclimates? All of the awesome microlandscapes you get acquainted with. Working at such small scales means you often get to appreciate the little things in life as you sometimes spend half an hour without moving more than a meter.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/Collage1.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    One of the best parts about working with microclimates? All of the awesome microlandscapes you get acquainted with. Working at such small scales means you often get to appreciate the little things in life as you sometimes spend half an hour without moving more than a meter.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting one of the elements in this course is the application of traits-based in climate change research. Climate change is globally a bit of a hot topic and it will be interesting to see what public perception of it will be in Peru. Having grown up in South Africa and now living in Sweden it is interesting to see how not only the government but also the public view the issue of climate change. Sweden is very ‘climate conscious’ and the general public has really bought into the idea of ‘green living’, it’s even part of political campaigns and debates. Back home the picture is slightly different. I think most people would agree with you that the climate is changing (I mean we have had serious droughts and heatwaves the last few years) but I don’t think that people have realised that they can and should start taking action regarding their lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think if I had to put Peru on the same continuum, they would be closer to South Africa than Sweden. Although they may not have the strong dependence on agriculture (and thus ‘good’ weather) I am sure they will still feel the effects of changes in temperature/rainfall that affects crop production. The recent appearance of the rainbow mountains near Cuzco is another undeniable proof of the changing climate. Therefore, I think that the public probably doesn’t doubt that climate change is happening, but I do wonder how much they link it to human actions/activities or see themselves as ‘culprits’ when compared to countries such as the US or China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I am excited for these next two weeks and look forward to putting some of these questions to bed during my stay and leaving Peru with a whole new set of tools in my toolbox and hopefully some new friends! And if all else fails at least I got to have my own &lt;em&gt;‘sportlov’&lt;/em&gt; playing in the mountains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;🐾
Tanya&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From a crisis to an opportunity: Eight insights for doing science in the Covid-19 era and beyond</title>
      <link>/publication/preprint/8insights/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/preprint/8insights/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
