<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>musings | Tanya Does Science</title>
    <link>/tag/musings/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/musings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>musings</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon.png</url>
      <title>musings</title>
      <link>/tag/musings/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Science is the music and data visualisation is the symphony</title>
      <link>/post/science-is-the-music-and-data-visualisation-is-the-symphony/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/science-is-the-music-and-data-visualisation-is-the-symphony/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’m definitely not the first (nor will I be the last) person to try and draw links between science and music but a recent(ish) tweet by Richard McElreath got me thinking on the idea a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34;&gt;
&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
Many performers of music cannot read it. Okay. There are other, often more intuitive, ways to learn music.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Scientists perform stat models. Most scientists cannot read them. This is less OK, but there are other ways to learn models.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Short thread in which I strain this comparison &lt;a href=&#34;https://t.co/WP8m6554PQ&#34;&gt;pic.twitter.com/WP8m6554PQ&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
— Richard McElreath 🦔 (&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@rlmcelreath&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/rlmcelreath/status/1284426933749653504?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&#34;&gt;July 18, 2020&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this thread McElreath discusses the similarities between reading sheet music and mathematical notations - if you don’t know where to start it can all be pretty daunting and even if you do know where to start you don’t necessarily read it ‘word-for-word’. Now, as someone who dabbles in both sides of this argument I couldn’t agree more. Mathematical notation can be scary but if you look for patterns/elements that you recognise you can work out what the model is telling you and the same can be said when I’m looking at sheet music. The same goes for the ‘degrees of separation’ and sheet music/models that are closer to my area of study/instrument of choice require less work to ‘decode’ than those that may be drastically different. McElreath goes on to discuss ‘maths anxiety’ and how that may be off-putting (or even scary for some) and some have shown this to indeed be the case [refs]. He also mentions maybe making mathematical notation more palatable - and here is where he caught my attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hans Rosling has also made links to science and music:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Most of us need to listen to the music to understand how beautiful it is. But often that’s how we present statistics: we just show the notes, we don’t play the music.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and his argument is perhaps a bit more elegantly phrased and absolutely nails it id you ask me. If statistics (or equations and models) is the sheet music then we as the scientists or researchers are the conductors. It is the responsibility (and vision) of the conductor to translate what he sees on paper and make it art as well as something the general public can perceive and enjoy. The conductor does this by directing and ‘using’ the musicians to create the final product. The reason I use an orchestra as opposed to a single musician here in my analogy is that I feel there are many ‘tools’ we can use to communicate the ‘scary maths’ and what we can learn from it, and much like how some scores play to the strengths of certain instruments so do some of the communication tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having just said that I’m going to focus in on my all time favourite way of communicating science - visually! Hans Rosling is well known for his excellent visualisations - and data visualisation is on the rise. A quick google search will yield multiple hits of different websites listing their top dataViz books. Yet why has the sciences lagged behind? With most (if not all) people accessing articles or resources online we do not have to worry about printing of or fitting figures and tables onto pages. We could potentially even embed links that lead to interactive dashboard-type applications or even animations. There are some other concerns such as accessibility and limited connectivity but as it stands there is no reason we can add richer visuals elements to our work. I think visual abstracts are a step in the right direction but what is to say we cannot extend this same ‘light hearted’ approach to the manuscript itself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve always joked that one day I will write a totally visual manuscript (Intro = digram/flowchart, Methods = schematic diagram, Results = plots and tables, and Discussion = diagram/flowchart) The thinking behind this is that I find it easier to articulate myself in a visual manner and almost all of my writing starts with me drawing a picture of what I plan on saying. This of course also means that I find it easier to visualise/draw what I am learning or reading as well - so it only stands to reason that the more visual elements a manuscript has the easier it is for me (and likely others) to get the bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I guess what this boils down to is me challenging the scientific community to think about how they can make beautiful music and ask if they are getting the best out of their orchestra. If you have a visual aid that is well designed it can break down at least some of the language barriers and make your work easier to understand for a non-native speaker, you are ‘forced’ to cut out a lot of jargon which makes your work more interpretable across disciplines - or even less experienced individuals (I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; don’t want to say non-scientists) or students and in a way you have to think harder about what your data are telling you, because if you don’t understand what is going it makes it very hard to translate that into a picture. Finally, to bring it back to the music analogy - much like how I would annotate my sheet music to make it easier to interpret we can also add other aids (annotations) along with our visualisations to help make the interpretation process easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is me challenging you to play with your data a bit more and see what it wants to show you - and it doesn’t have to be fancy it can start with playing with colours and then the more comfortable you get the more you can stretch you boundaries. This is where projects like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tidytuesday.com&#34;&gt;#TidyTuesday&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.makeovermonday.co.uk&#34;&gt;#MakeoverMonday&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.storytellingwithdata.com/swdchallenge&#34;&gt;Story Telling with Data challenge&lt;/a&gt; are really - you can play with data in a ‘low pressure’ environment and get inspiration from others as to how they approached the same challenge and help you familiarize yourself with different plot types - helping you develop a library of sorts and a bit of a personal style. So much like how a conductor adds his own flair to sonata/concerto so can you make your data visualisation your own!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have fun creating and pushing the envelope for data visualisation in science&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tanya&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coming to Terms With Being a Theoretical Ecologist</title>
      <link>/post/coming-to-terms-with-being-a-theoretical-ecologist/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/coming-to-terms-with-being-a-theoretical-ecologist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;While trawling through the interweb looking at advertised PhD positions (as well as stalking some of my favourite researchers) I started to notice a bit of a trend - the topics that I found interesting weren&amp;rsquo;t always linked to a strong field component but rather had fancy statistical and mathematical terms somewhere in the project description (process based modelling and machine learning anyone??). I love being outside, absolutely adore it actually, and always thought the appeal of ecology was the chance to go out to wild and exotic places and do some cool data collecting along the way. But the more I think about the more I think that was just the sun-loving, adrenaline junkie in me&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My analytical brain (I blame having two engineers as parents for this) on the other hand &lt;em&gt;loves&lt;/em&gt; the data analysis and processing side of things - more specifically playing with and (hopefully) being able to draw meaningful conclusions from the data. I get super excited (and geek out extensively) about all of the cool things and stories I can learn from the data that we&amp;rsquo;ve collected. Only to be (mildly) upset when I discover that we don&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; have enough or all of the data needed to apply the really cool or complex approaches that I would like to take and then being relegated to the more &amp;lsquo;vanilla&amp;rsquo; statistical analyses. But if I think back on it long enough I think it goes back even further than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fondly remember one day in first year over a cup of tea a friend and I were joking about developing a &amp;lsquo;master&amp;rsquo; formula that we could use for all of our calculations for the upcoming physics exam (I mean realistically they&amp;rsquo;re all interconnected but in our defence it was first yet and we were exhausted/delirious). Fast forward to my more recent musings I found myself in a philosophy course where I often brought up how we as ecologists really don&amp;rsquo;t seem to have any concrete laws (except maybe the species area relationship) or that they at least require a fair bit of hand waving and that we don&amp;rsquo;t seem to be actively moving towards that (data synthesis) direction either (&lt;em&gt;Although I do think that is changing&lt;/em&gt;). Clearly that is what I crave though - developing and working with a model/formula/program that I can apply to my specific research query.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another tell-tale sign should have been how quickly I adopted the use of functional traits in my data collecting/consideration protocol. I love the concept, not only can we use them to quantify certain ecosystem processes, but we also create an abstraction of the individual - everyone is reduced to their trait value(s) and treated as such. So not only are we able to take data from individuals (and communities) and scale this up to infer various ecosystem processes we also have a sense of generality by using traits. All species (at least within some taxonomic group) share the same traits they are just expressed differently - all plants (if we stick with vascular species) have leaves and as such we can &amp;lsquo;reduce&amp;rsquo; them all to the traits of their leaves e.g. area/mass/water content. This means that we could use these traits in our analyses and would be more likely to make generalisations of our conclusions by saying if an individual has &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; traits we expect it to respond in such a manner to changes in temperature. Now isn&amp;rsquo;t that an elegant approach!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other warning signs probably include the fact that I am very happy when I have R studio open in one window and Stack Overflow in another and have spent the last hour trying to work out why the code that was working has now decided to no longer co-operate. Another may have been me deciding that I &lt;del&gt;needed&lt;/del&gt; wanted to take a course in Bayesian Analyses (despite it being a bit of an admin headache) because it &amp;ldquo;looks really cool&amp;rdquo;. Admittedly this was also when I found out about hierarchical modelling and let me tell you it was love at first sight! Well until I found out that there are even more things you can do by building on that concept&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I have to face the music and accept that I probably love sitting in front of my computer thinking about species in abstract terms and numbers more than being out in the field doing the data collecting - and I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m okay with that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tanya &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;a self-diagnosed theoretical ecologist. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Home is… What your passport says?</title>
      <link>/post/home-is-what-your-passport-says/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/home-is-what-your-passport-says/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;
*“Could you pass the tomato sauce?”*
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The what?!?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The tomato sauce.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Oh, you mean the ketchup!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Yeah that”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: justify&#34;&gt;
Just a typical conversation at the dinner table between the many international students attending the fifth plant functional traits course in Perú co-hosted by the University of Bergen and Arizona. Most of our conversations are punctuated by local colloquialisms and some even take on a bilingual flair (“How would you say that in *insert language*?” or “We would say it like this in *insert language*.”). However, these idiosyncrasies are not only limited to our everyday conversations and our discussions revolving around science often have many diverse takes. 
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward and the COVID-19 pandemic has wreaked havoc on global transportation networks. With Perú being one of the countries to declare a state of emergency and closing all borders and internal travel resulting in half of us being stranded. The awesome multinational cast of researchers that we are means that we’re now faced with a bit of a conundrum. We all belong to different institutions and countries – with many of us not even studying in our home country. Who do we belong to? Who is responsible for helping us get home?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I can tell you this, a residence permit only means so much – and support from your home institution? Don’t put too much stake on that! Having dual citizenship myself, and living in a third country while doing my Masters you’d think I’d have many avenues to pursue to try and get out. Well, the country I currently live (and have residence) in simply turned me away and my home country was of no assistance. The only light at the end of the tunnel – my second nationality – a country that I’ve never even lived in! Many of us were in the same boat, with most institutions dragging their feet to give any support (although a special shout out to the guys at Bergen) and having to just wait it out until our different governments could (hopefully) help us out.&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-the-empty-streets-of-cusco-during-the-lockdown-normally-these-alleys-would-be-packed-with-locals-and-tourists-alike&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/Streets.jpeg&#34; data-caption=&#34;The empty streets of Cusco during the lockdown. Normally these alleys would be packed with locals and tourists alike.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/Streets.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    The empty streets of Cusco during the lockdown. Normally these alleys would be packed with locals and tourists alike.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, one could argue that we put ourselves in this situation. Going off to a developing country in what appears to be an emerging pandemic only to go out and ‘mess-around’ in the mountains in the name of science. But it’s so much more than that. As much as I was looking forward to learning about the science side of things the part of the course that I found the most attractive was the chance to meet so many international researchers. Science is after all a social activity and, with the ease of long-distance communication, collaborative projects can often span the globe. So, in reality this course is but a snapshot of what science looks like and how things work and working abroad is not uncommon. So, the question is should we stop trying to be globe trotters and just keep it local? Return back to a time when it was ‘us’ vs. ‘them’? Should we just dismantle the global science community?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it’s time that institutions actually take some responsibility for their employees. After all, we oftentimes uproot our whole lives to work with them, the least they could do is have our backs in times of crisis. We shouldn’t have to rely on the ‘back-up’ support from consulates and embassies – our institutions should be fighting for us too! I think if we were to ‘localise’ our science within country and institutional borders in fear of unknown disasters we would only be hamstringing that which we hold dear. We would be losing out on input of researchers from different cultural and sociological backgrounds and ultimately their unique take on that which we call science. In addition, localising science would mean missing out on &lt;del&gt;heated&lt;/del&gt; extensive conversations regarding the correct pronunciation of words – I’m looking at you Americans! 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tanya&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a more eloquent take have a look at this PopSci article that we wrote about our experience 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.timeshighereducation.com/blog/international-scientists-need-better-support-during-global-emergencies&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
