<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>EcologicalNetworks | Tanya Does Science</title>
    <link>/tag/ecologicalnetworks/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/ecologicalnetworks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>EcologicalNetworks</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon.png</url>
      <title>EcologicalNetworks</title>
      <link>/tag/ecologicalnetworks/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>SVD entropy reveals the high complexity of ecological networks</title>
      <link>/publication/preprint/svdent/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/preprint/svdent/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Making better predictions of ecological networks through machine learning (done right)</title>
      <link>/project/networkpredictions/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/networkpredictions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So after a month of biweekly meetings we have a working draft and let me tell you things are HOT!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quantifying the complexity of ecological networks has remained elusive. Primarily, complexity has been defined on the basis of the structural (or behavioural) complexity of the system. These definitions ignore the notion of &amp;lsquo;physical complexity&amp;rsquo;, which can measure the amount of information contained in an ecological network, and how difficult it would be to compress. We present relative rank deficiency and SVD entropy as measures of &amp;lsquo;external&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;internal&amp;rsquo; complexity respectively. Using bipartite ecological networks, we find that they all show a very high, almost maximal, physical complexity. Pollination networks, in particular, are more complex when compared to other types of interactions. In addition, we find that SVD entropy relates to other structural measures of complexity (nestedness, connectance, and spectral radius), but does not inform about the resilience of a network when using simulated extinction cascades, which has previously been reported for structural measures of complexity. We argue that SVD entropy provides a fundamentally more &amp;lsquo;correct&amp;rsquo; measure of network complexity and should be added to the toolkit of descriptors of ecological networks moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;mutualistic&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SVD entropy reveals the high complexity of ecological networks</title>
      <link>/project/svdnetworks/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/svdnetworks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As a quick primer: generally in ecology we have struggled to define the complexity of ecological networks. Many measures have been proposed, with these usually focusing on the &lt;em&gt;structural&lt;/em&gt; complexity of the network as opposed to using the &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;physical&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; complexity of the network. Here we used SVD entropy (based off of information theory) as well as the relative rank deficiency to quantify complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we use the SVD entropy of a network we are looking at the information that is contained within the interaction matrix of the system - broadly how much information is contained with each species and the interaction strategy it has adopted. Many other attempts at trying to quantify the complexity of ecological networks look more at the structure i.e. the behaviour of the interaction network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly we found that ecological networks are very complex - in theory SVD entropy can take a value from 0 - 1 yet all of our networks were above 0.8&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;/img/SVD.png&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;/img/SVD.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The long and the short of it is that we argue that using an information based approach to quantifying the complexity of a network is a more &amp;lsquo;correct&amp;rsquo; approach than those that focus on structure. If we unify this definition it will hopefully allow us to uncover more general patterns or relationship with complexity - e.g. the argument that complexity begets stability.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
