<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>SingularValueDecomposition | Tanya Does Science</title>
    <link>/tag/singularvaluedecomposition/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/singularvaluedecomposition/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>SingularValueDecomposition</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon.png</url>
      <title>SingularValueDecomposition</title>
      <link>/tag/singularvaluedecomposition/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>SVD entropy reveals the high complexity of ecological networks</title>
      <link>/publication/journal-article/svdent/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/journal-article/svdent/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fast-tracking the PhD Experience</title>
      <link>/post/fast-tracking-the-phd-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/fast-tracking-the-phd-experience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Can I just humorously preface this by saying that the email from the journal saying that they had received the manuscript addressed me as Dr Strydom and can&amp;rsquo;t say that I hate it - although maybe a &lt;em&gt;bit&lt;/em&gt; premature 😉 Oh and maybe as another add on - working in different timezones may be annoying in terms of scheduling meetings but it is pretty great when you wake up in the mornings to &amp;lsquo;good job&amp;rsquo; messages from your supervisor 😁&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not going to talk about the actual theory/content of the manuscript (because that I&amp;rsquo;m saving for the actual project page) but rather just talk about how being thrown into the deep end by your supervisor (but having him also throw you a very effective form of floatation device) results in quickly learning things in a driven manner, especially some handy collaborative workflow things that are also very Open Science and FAIR aligned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;publishing-so-soon&#34;&gt;Publishing so soon?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look I&amp;rsquo;m not saying that all graduate students &lt;strong&gt;need&lt;/strong&gt; to publish something right of the bat - and its a case of student readiness and opportunity that needs to be taken into consideration. However, that being said it makes for a fun way to help and encourage the student to get up to speed with literature and have it be in a rewarding manner (in a sense) as the student has a short-term goal to achieve. I also felt like it took away some of the daunting feeling of &amp;lsquo;where do we even start?&amp;rsquo; after starting. It&amp;rsquo;s also a really great confidence boost and makes you feel like a &amp;lsquo;scientist&amp;rsquo;. Ultimately it also means that I have something &amp;lsquo;to show&amp;rsquo; when I take my candidacy exam in a few months time - hopefully impressing the advisory board 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-coding-language---sure-why-not&#34;&gt;New coding language - sure why not?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I knew going into this that learning how to work in &lt;code&gt;Julia&lt;/code&gt; was going to be inevitable - &lt;em&gt;&amp;lsquo;it&amp;rsquo;s the way&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;/author/poisot-lab/&#34;&gt;Poisot Lab&lt;/a&gt; after all. However, that being said learning, and &lt;del&gt;struggling&lt;/del&gt; pottering along with a new coding language when the submission deadline is seemingly in the distance is all fun and games, when its two days before d-day - not so fun. But overall its nice to work on a small, manageable chunk of the Julia-verse and a lot of the functions I was writing were simple arithmetic so it was a nice to work in a &amp;lsquo;low stakes&amp;rsquo; situation with regards to getting to grips with how to write function and the &amp;lsquo;types&amp;rsquo; that you can specify in &lt;code&gt;Julia&lt;/code&gt;. It also helps that after my toddler like attempt at writing a function  my supervisor steps in and directs/shows me where I erred or what is a more &amp;lsquo;grammatically correct&amp;rsquo; way of approaching the problem. Essentially I had a small and &amp;lsquo;contained&amp;rsquo; crash course in a new programming language that will hopefully set me up for success further down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;are-you-not-entertained&#34;&gt;Are you not entertained?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know what&amp;rsquo;s the best part of my fast-tracked experience? It&amp;rsquo;s really helped build back some of the excitement and enjoyment for research and science-ing that I felt my masters had &amp;lsquo;taken&amp;rsquo; from me. It also helps that my supervisor is very excited about everything we&amp;rsquo;ve done and I can&amp;rsquo;t help but feed off of that! It&amp;rsquo;s also very entertaining collaborating over GitHub with someone for both coding and writing and let me tell you its getting even more exciting regarding GitHub collaborating for our next project (The predicting ecological networks one if you&amp;rsquo;re wondering). I think (hopefully one day) I&amp;rsquo;ll write up a quick primer on collaborative writing over GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cheers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tanya 🐾&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project Malcolm</title>
      <link>/project/projectmalcolm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/projectmalcolm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;singular-value-decomposition-a-multitool-for-network-ecology&#34;&gt;Singular value decomposition: a multitool for network ecology&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ecological networks can be represented by their adjacency matrices, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;
a matrix for which every entry represents a species pair, and takes either
a value of 1 if there is an interaction between the two species, or 0
when there is none. Singular Value Decomposition ([SVD)
is the factorisation of a matrix $\mathbf{A}$
(where $\mathbf{A}_{m,n} \in\mathbb{B}$, in the context of adjacency matrices) into the form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathbf{U}\cdot\mathbf{\Sigma}\cdot\mathbf{V}^T $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where $\mathbf{U}$ is an $m \times m$ orthogonal matrix and
$\mathbf{V}$ an $n \times n$ orthogonal matrix. The columns in these matrices
are, respectively, the left- and right-singular vectors of $\mathbf{A}$.
$\mathbf{\Sigma}$ is a diagonal matrix that contains only non-negative $\sigma$
values. Where $\sigma_{i} = \Sigma{ii}$, and contains the singular values of
$\mathbf{A}$. When the values of $\mathbf{\sigma}$ are arranged in
descending order, the singular values ($\mathbf{\Sigma}$) are
unique. These singular values can broadly be viewed as a measure of
how informative that rank of the matrix is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;svd-entropy-as-a-measure-of-complexity&#34;&gt;SVD Entropy as a measure of complexity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can use SVD and more specifically SVD entropy as a measure of network complexity.
This approach looks at the &amp;lsquo;physical complexity&amp;rsquo; of networks - which is in
contrast to more traditional measures such as connectence and nestedness which
look at the &amp;lsquo;behavioural complexity&amp;rsquo; of networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;svd-entropy-and-network-assembly&#34;&gt;SVD Entropy and network assembly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An additional concept that I want to explore (if there is enough time) is the
relationship between network assembly and constraints on complexity (SVD entropy).
This will be building on a small section of the SVD entropy manuscript&lt;br&gt;
relating to network assembly and the constraints on complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
