<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>MachineLearning | Tanya Does Science</title>
    <link>/tag/machinelearning/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/machinelearning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>MachineLearning</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon.png</url>
      <title>MachineLearning</title>
      <link>/tag/machinelearning/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Food web reconstruction through phylogenetic transfer of low-rank network representation</title>
      <link>/publication/preprint/recfoo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/preprint/recfoo/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project Wombat</title>
      <link>/project/projectwombat/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/projectwombat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;space-and-networks-the-wild-frontier&#34;&gt;Space (and networks): The wild frontier&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project will focus on
the variation of networks across space. More explicitly the idea of trying to
delineate networks into discrete patches (ecotrophic zones) by drawing boundaries
based on areas of rapid change. Spatial wombling will be used as the edge
detection method. This project will have three components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;developing-a-spatial-boundaries-package&#34;&gt;Developing a spatial boundaries package&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first will be to develop a &lt;em&gt;Julia&lt;/em&gt; package that implements the wombling
algorithm. This will be submitted the &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Open Science&lt;/em&gt; as a
software package/manuscript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;detecting-boundaries-of-networks-in-the-landscape&#34;&gt;Detecting boundaries of networks in the landscape&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second phase will focus on how network boundaries
in a landscape compare to other community metrics such as species composition or
turnover and will result in a methods/perspectives type piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-does-the-within-structure-of-networks-vary&#34;&gt;How does the within structure of networks vary?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third (and
arguably most interesting) phase will focus more on structural changes within
networks across space and lean heavily on using motifs and graphlet theory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Roadmap Toward Predicting Species Interaction Networks (Across Space and Time)</title>
      <link>/publication/preprint/pripre/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/preprint/pripre/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project One Ring</title>
      <link>/project/projectonering/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/projectonering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Providing an overview of the
toolset that we would need to predict networks across both time and space.
The core idea behind this project is to produce a roadmap for grad student by
grad students envisioning the future quests we could conceivably go on. The
primary focus is on the need to develop a multi-faceted way to begin the
conceptualisation network prediction as well as taking advantage of the growth
of complex computational tools and the availability of data to facilitate the
prediction process&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project Pokédex</title>
      <link>/project/projectpokedex/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/projectpokedex/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project focuses on assembling the Canadian terrestrial metaweb and will,
in a way, be a &amp;lsquo;testing ground&amp;rsquo; for some of the concepts from other projects
(&lt;em&gt;i.e&lt;/em&gt; phylogenetic inference of ecological interactions through network
embedding, more so the idea of using a &lt;em&gt;t-SVD&lt;/em&gt; as the basis of this process)
as well as incorporating some of the points outlined and discussed in chapter two. This
project forms part of a CIEE working group and, in addition to this prediction focused
component will also feature an expert elicitation project which will be
and used as a complement to the computational approach. These different approaches
will ultimately be combined into one metaweb to rule them all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;icouldnevertaketheplaceofyourmammal&#34;&gt;ICouldNeverTakeThePlaceofyourMammal&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve been doing some interim work with the mammalian component of the&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project Malcolm</title>
      <link>/project/projectmalcolm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/projectmalcolm/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;singular-value-decomposition-a-multitool-for-network-ecology&#34;&gt;Singular value decomposition: a multitool for network ecology&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ecological networks can be represented by their adjacency matrices, &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt;
a matrix for which every entry represents a species pair, and takes either
a value of 1 if there is an interaction between the two species, or 0
when there is none. Singular Value Decomposition ([SVD)
is the factorisation of a matrix $\mathbf{A}$
(where $\mathbf{A}_{m,n} \in\mathbb{B}$, in the context of adjacency matrices) into the form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mathbf{U}\cdot\mathbf{\Sigma}\cdot\mathbf{V}^T $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where $\mathbf{U}$ is an $m \times m$ orthogonal matrix and
$\mathbf{V}$ an $n \times n$ orthogonal matrix. The columns in these matrices
are, respectively, the left- and right-singular vectors of $\mathbf{A}$.
$\mathbf{\Sigma}$ is a diagonal matrix that contains only non-negative $\sigma$
values. Where $\sigma_{i} = \Sigma{ii}$, and contains the singular values of
$\mathbf{A}$. When the values of $\mathbf{\sigma}$ are arranged in
descending order, the singular values ($\mathbf{\Sigma}$) are
unique. These singular values can broadly be viewed as a measure of
how informative that rank of the matrix is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;svd-entropy-as-a-measure-of-complexity&#34;&gt;SVD Entropy as a measure of complexity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can use SVD and more specifically SVD entropy as a measure of network complexity.
This approach looks at the &amp;lsquo;physical complexity&amp;rsquo; of networks - which is in
contrast to more traditional measures such as connectence and nestedness which
look at the &amp;lsquo;behavioural complexity&amp;rsquo; of networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;svd-entropy-and-network-assembly&#34;&gt;SVD Entropy and network assembly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An additional concept that I want to explore (if there is enough time) is the
relationship between network assembly and constraints on complexity (SVD entropy).
This will be building on a small section of the SVD entropy manuscript&lt;br&gt;
relating to network assembly and the constraints on complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
